this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet as the
radio brings you relevant and detailed
discussions and interviews on software
engineering topics every two weeks
thanks to our audience and the partners
listed on our web site for supporting
the podcast welcome listeners to new
episode of software engineering radio
this is the third one we recall that
Chow 2008 in Aarhus in Denmark and this
time we're going to talk about API API
designs and general concerns when
dealing with API sand our guest today is
Jim deliver yeah I hope this is
pronounced correctly yes very good hi
Jim hi Marcus well before we talk about
the topic why don't you introduce
yourself to our listeners briefly
currently I work for IBM I work with the
Eclipse and Jazz teams helping to to get
api's in place in some places I've
actually done some of the the heavy
lifting of of actually defining the API
is in other places and so much more
common I've worked with the teams and
helped them to form their api's and
maintain them and evolve them over the
over the years mm-hm
so well obviously this discussions about
API so why don't we start by kind of
defining or explaining what an API is
very simply the API it was an
application program or interface is the
acronym spelled out and the the
particular characteristics of it that
are important is that you have some kind
of specified interface that sits between
a basically a client on one side and an
implementation on the other side two
pieces of code the interface itself has
a specification in the case of an API in
the Java sense that's basically the Java
doc so so do you consider the only well
okay that's good part is the API the the
code that represents it represents the
interface or is it the documentation
that describes the code it's actually
it's not the running code it's
it's the particular Javadoc that's
decorating those particular elements so
think of it this way and is that it's
it's really what you're doing when you
specify an interface is you're painting
a picture of various kinds of classes
methods related things a certain set of
concepts that the client of the API is
going to need to understand in order to
be able to use that API to solve their
particular problem and certainly they're
going to have to be aware of the
particular methods in classes but the
thing that's really important is they
have to know what those methods and
classes do do yeah the semantics
semantics of things what are the input
parameters output parameters what what
do they mean and also getting it more
into the sort of the actual the overview
of how all the pieces of the API fit
together which in the in case of a
regular raw Java API would be you know
package level and class level Java dog
but it's all of the same thing it's
words in the normal case the tell the
client what they need to know in order
to be able to use the API effectively so
some people well some people think that
an API should be specified more formally
however you do this I don't know
protocol state machine Cyprian
post-conditions do you think it's it's a
problem that api's are specified in
plain english mostly or is it good
because the that at the point of the API
is to tell a story to the client how to
use it I I think it's actually generally
good that they're written in English
because the the most important thing is
to be able to tell the client or I
should probably be more careful and
things the consumer of that API the
actual programmer who's gonna be writing
the client-side code yeah they are the
ones that actually have to understand
that it that what the particular API is
giving them and they're going to have to
understand to use it that's sort of the
first client formalization in that
doesn't necessarily help the human
reader that or formalization of
preconditions and postconditions
can help is with other tools and other
programs that could reason a
about that API but first and foremost
the API it has got to get its its
consumers and then those are people and
yeah yeah so so if we do an episode
about API design an API is why our API
is so important I mean obviously they
are a kind of contract but our what are
the challenges and you know the
specifics about why API is how the
central piece I guess in your mind about
defining systems well one of the things
that is important about API is is if you
actually look look around api's are
absolutely everywhere
they're very very important to us
economically
they're certainly a thriving industry
we're developing more api's all the time
and they're actually nothing new I mean
we've always always lived in a world of
computation where we have api's or
things like api specs that phenomena has
has always been with us and so the the
question that that I was was sort of
interested in exploring is well well
what is it about them that makes them so
important yeah I believe at the heart of
it the fundamental reason that they're
so important to us is that they're a way
that we can as humans the programmers
who are building the system we can deal
with the fact that we need to build an
arbitrarily complicated system but we
actually have to deal with the fact that
as programmers we have limited
capabilities as humans right now we
can't remember absolutely an infinite
amount of data we have to do some kind
of chunking and what's happening with
api's abstractions all the things that
are sort of in that camp are mechanisms
that we use and always have used for
breaking down the program into mind
sized pieces
so that we can actually tackle them
either as it as individual humans or as
as actual teams of people who were
working in building these building these
systems and the thing that's striking
about it is we
never been we've we've never found any
other way that we can approach problems
essentially on a large scale building
systems on a large scale without doing
this kind of basic divide and conquer
and where we cut up the the program into
pieces that we can actually we can deal
with and it's striking also that the the
techniques that we use really scale
linearly in the size of the actual
program so a gigantic program like the
Windows XP in a couple of years back the
size of that codebase was estimated at
about forty million lines of code F and
that if you could read a thousand lines
of day that would take 120 years for one
person to actually read a program that
size but obviously we don't have to
understand the program in to end to be
able to reason about its property if it
has seams partitions and various kinds
of levels going on inside it and that
kind of chunking is absolutely essential
and it's what it allows us to actually
understand these big systems so in some
sense an API is the way to express a
certain abstraction in a programming
language yes because the API is a way to
express a from the perspective of the
user that's to the actual client is
generally a a client facing contract
yeah so what why why what's what's the
challenge to developers when working
with API is from the perspective of
defining and and also from the
perspective of using again is I guess
defining it is the bigger struggle
because using it I mean you just have to
live with what you get right defining it
is definitely the the bigger struggle I
was actually I was interested in in sort
of a numerating a number of different
struggles that we have because these
api's aren't they're not easy for us I
mean we have lots of them so yeah we can
basically deal with them but
there there are all sorts of of
struggles so one of the things that I
wanted to to basically do is sort of but
in the presentation which I I do today I
wanted to actually start a conversation
about what exactly is going on behind
this very obvious phenomenon and one
conjecture that I I have is that
although we all think of this as being a
completely obvious phenomenon I think we
actually that there are differences
amongst us as to how we understand that
phenomena and we don't all share exactly
the same understanding of what we all
considered obvious and of course one of
the problems with things that are
obvious is that it's our language rules
make it rude to talk about all these
things you know it's so obvious why
would we talk about this everybody knows
it but I think there's actually some
underneath it there's some different
understandings of what is actually going
on and the relative importance of those
detectors and I think api's is a way of
sort of drawing attention to there's
some very interesting things that are
going on so so what distinguishes a good
API from a bad API I think in the first
instance I would have to if I was gonna
judge an API its how well does it meet
the needs of the consumers of that API
right and what's what kind of problems
does it solve for them how large a class
of of of clients does it support how
easy does it make for make those clients
so it's possible to be written and
expressed in a in a way that the people
who are writing it can understand it
right so in some sense it's the two
things that you want on the table is
here's the API that I'm using and here's
the code that I'm writing to solve my my
problem in terms of that API those are
the things that the programmer has to
have on the table
and you want to judge the API as does it
enable someone to actually write that
program and when they look at this
program is it a such a program that they
can understand yeah yeah and the I think
secondary consideration also important
is the kinds of room to breathe that it
allows for what goes on behind the API
in terms of different ways flexibility
in terms of implementing it usually an
API will necessarily focus on certain
things that are important to the
particular clients of the consumer of
the API it'll give them a convenient
abstraction to work with and hide a lot
of details and often in in you know
complicated complicated systems there's
an awful lot of mechanism that goes on
behind the scene that it's simpler if
you can find a way to insulate the
client from that yeah so that they never
have to know the details so who should
design the API actually is it more the
the the implementer of the functionality
who is then obviously biased
to define the API in a way that is kind
of influenced by the way he built it or
is it better if the user the client
builds or strongly influences the API
because they have the scenarios in mind
that that govern how the API is going to
be used it's actually it's somewhere in
the middle it's walking this very fine
line to design a good API you definitely
you want to design it for the clients
you want to hear what clients are going
to do you have to be aware of how it's
going to be implemented in the kind of
room that you have to implement it but
you don't want to be to unduly biased by
either side right clients tend if you
had to say sort of as a class the tyent
clients will tend to push their problem
when they have a specific problem
they're trying to solve they will try to
tend to push that into the API itself
and likewise an implementer is
more likely to expose some part of the
mechanism underneath that they think is
particularly significant or important
but a good API designer may be actually
able to go in and sort of say look I can
explain what's going on to the
satisfaction of the clients without
having to reveal those details so it
really is as I titled to talk you know
API is drawing a line in the sand yeah
is this line and the best person to to
do that is someone who can actually walk
the line decide where that line is going
to be and then play both sides to
actually sort of argue with the clients
that they're giving them enough
functionality to solve their problem and
to argue with the implementers that
they're exposing just the right amount
of information to make a client happy
and leaving lots of breathing room on
the other side if you have several
scenarios that access the same module do
you think it's better to have one API
that can ideally cater for all those
different scenarios or is it better to
have several api's so that the code for
each of the clients that might do
different things is kind of optimally
readable and optimally understandable I
don't know whether I could could give a
definitive answer one way or another on
that kind of thing
the difficulty with having multiple
especially multiple API is backed on us
sort of common implementation is you
have to actually make the story seamless
to both of the parties and the analogy I
use this an API it's like a cover story
in a spy novel where you actually what
you do is you come up with this story
that discloses sufficient details it's
plausible self consistent and enough to
stop the people who are asking you
deeper questions and essentially a way
to
hide the actual truth of what's going on
and I think a good API is indeed trying
to hide a lot of the truth of what will
go in behind the scenes and the problem
when you have two api's backed on a
common thing is you have to actually
make the world seem coherent to both
parties but again if you have data or
something that could be created by a
party on one side but then access them
party on the other side it has to be
plausible on on both things it's easier
in situations where you you're saying
writing it reading and writing it
through one API but only reading it
through some of the other API yeah those
ones tend to be yeah MZ r to get a
variety and ones were you both of them
are they have different stories and
they're both able to read and write then
it becomes more of a challenge to come
up with a story that keeps them in sync
so one thing that seems to be a
recurring issue in in our in our
industry is that we work with all kinds
of things just to name a few components
architecture patterns and maybe api's
which play an important role in our well
in our daily work but our tools and our
languages don't really aren't really
able to express them as first-class
citizens I mean an API in Java is
basically an interface and documentation
is there is there any way to to maybe
you know improve tooling so that it can
do stuff for you that is specific to API
yes and what would that be definitely
the tools can help I mean the example I
think of it in the early days of text
editors knew nothing about the actual
language yeah that was being sort of
written in the file later we actually
had syntax coloring things which were
starting to be aware of the syntax of
language nowadays were were all quite
comfortable with having refactoring
browsers that know about the semantics
of the language and allow the actual
programmer to make transformations and
it can help to preserve the actual
meaning of the program
if the tools know where those api's are
they can be more sensitive and tailor
their particular actions in the presence
of the API so for example a refactoring
tool who knows where were the the api's
are won't
for example propose or don't have to
propose refactorings that's cross the
api boundary right or it could warn the
clients especially of it or an example
is in the eclipse PDE the plug-in
development environment one of the
things that was added in a recent
release is lets the programmer map out
where the api's are and there's a tool
which now runs as part of the nightly
builds which actually compares the api
to a previous baseline and notices any
signature changes new methods coming in
and can print a report for the actual
developers that can even classify a
particular change that ceases being a
particularly potentially breaking change
you know like deleting a public method
on an api class and how do you mark up
the API is it annotations or how do you
do it i'm it's a good question I don't
know the answer again so the I believe
it's a combination of information that's
in something that's like annotations but
I don't believe it's using the syntax
okay of the the actual annotation
processing facility in Java because part
of the eclipse code base is actually
earlier yeah then the annotations which
only came in a Java phone yeah but it's
that kind of information allows a tool
to be sensitive to where the API czar
and once it knows that it can actually
help and one day I hope to to see the
the refactoring engine in an Eclipse
also be yeah love the the API so that I
can actually go do better there one
underlying assumption that we've had but
we didn't actually explicitly mention
that is that of course one important
characteristic of API is that they are
stable over time or at least backward
compatible
to talk a little bit about that well
that's anybody who has API is that's
always a very important issue in terms
of how how they're going to keep API
stable I mean by their nature the best
api's are the ones that don't change
right that allows the clients who have
actually written their programs against
a particular API it allows that code to
keep keep running without actually
having to be changed and that's very
important and that kind of stability is
important there's a certain kinds of
evolution that you can do particular in
in Java there's certain kind of things
like generally adding methods even
public methods to API classes things are
kinds of changes that can be done that
don't actually violate compatibility
with existing clients either right the
ones that haven't been written or
actually existing ones that have been
compiled binary version ability and
there's a a host of things that you can
do to the api's that won't break
compatibility and so that's the good
news
oh it helps to understand in advance of
designing a Java API understand Java
javis very specific rules for the binary
compatibility know what you can get away
with because it's actually a very very
sort of tricky technical thing to it
depends on yeah it's not intuitive at
all and it depends on the details of how
the compiler transforms source code into
the the byte codes and that is it's
prettier Kanan it's not what a normal
Java programmer knows there has any need
to know about what the details are and
so one of the documents which I had
produced going back several years now
available on the Eclipse website is a
guide to evolving Java API is in terms
of what kinds of things you can do
that don't break compatibility or when
you do do break compatibility which
kinds of clients you'll be breaking
breaking them with and why they're there
being broken if you have to break the
api compatibility than one pattern i see
an eclipse over and over again is that
there is actually a new api typically
called bla bla bla to which which is
explicitly different and clients have to
explicitly change their the API they use
so you avoid the accidental kind of
crash exactly and that's when when we've
done that and and we're not the the only
platform that does that kind of uses
that particular kind of pattern is it's
a way the old class still remains in
play and if your program is written
against the old class you get exactly
the same semantics that you were
guaranteed in this this earlier
incarnation and so this is a way of
adding the additional additional methods
it's the typical thing that happens but
add additional methods at a later point
without breaking compatibility yeah I
should point out that part of those
problems are I would describe as
self-inflicted in that we in the early
days of the Eclipse platform when a
number of these API is that you're
probably referring to when with these
these numbers on them those you get
particular fragility if you use Java
interfaces and particularly it's an
interface if you have an interface that
you expect the client-side to implement
then either adding or deleting methods
is a breaking change so you really are
locked in if you actually do much better
in a lot of cases to have abstract
classes and there's actually a very good
chapter and early on in Joshua blocks
look on effective Java that talks
exactly about
you know choice between using a Java
interface and using a java abstract
class to do these kinds of things in
there it's important to know that
because if you make the right choice
you'll have certain maneuvering room
down the road and on the other hand you
you use up java's only inheritance link
that's the disadvantage you use up the
inheritance link yes nothing's for free
and things so there is a general sense
in which with working within the rules
of what you can get away with in with
the Java language semantics you can't
actually do a fair amount in terms of
evolving an API but it's in a very
irregular set of rules
and you're much better off studying
those rules in advance and looking at
the various choices to see you know if
you think you may need to add a method
down the road to do something that you
can't anticipate right now you may want
to actually make certain choices between
classes and things are also whether you
have a callback style interface or
whether it just as a straight calling
now face it also makes a difference as
to who's implementing what and therefore
what changes are our braking changes if
I would say that every good API has to
be accompanied by a unit test or a set
of unit tests that verifies the
semantics is that is would you agree
absolutely the the most radical version
that that I would would propose
seriously proposed is in designing an
API you're writing this cover story for
the client the cover story is going to
be told in the particular class and
method signatures after the public
methods and their Javadoc comments and
that's where I would actually begin
writing that tell that story in the
actual methods and then once you've told
that story then start writing the unit
tests against such doing black box text
testing against the particular
api's which you now have specified yeah
and having the API in place allows you
tells you exactly what tests you're
going to actually have to write it also
tells you the information that you're
going to need to to be able to implement
the API in terms of what's the
observable behavior that the client is
going to be able to see and and
therefore the things that are are going
to be important the implementation gets
right all of that follows from having
the API spec in place right and so the
methodology that that I advocate and
that we we try to use an eclipse project
and and the J's project is what we call
API first base that you know take off on
that the test first approach where we
actually write the API specifications
and design the api's in advance of doing
the the actual implementation work and
one of the things which is I don't know
whether people would find it surprising
I I don't know how many people actually
have tried that kind of sort of extreme
let's just write the spec write the
story of how the thing is going to work
and do that before worrying about
anything else well I would say generally
most programmers are somewhat wired
differently right they want to write
real code which is the implementation I
don't write prose text that explains
what the code does yes a bit out of
fashion I guess I think that is that
that's what I think a lot of people's
reaction would be that somehow writing
these comments and everything
it is not much like programming and I
actually I have done this quite quite
extensively and one of the things is
actually quite striking is it it's very
much like programming even though you're
not actually writing the code you still
are using the same skills that you have
as a programmer because you're you're
imagining this world you know certain
abstractions describe this way here's
the method you're supposed to call this
passing these arguments we're going to
compute you this result
everything and you can write that
specification and as long as you're not
too far from home right in terms of
you're comfortable with all the
mechanisms that you were be under there
there's not really a whole lot of risk
that you would write a clean
specification like this and not actually
be able to implement it now and so when
you realize that you write the
specification it's like well that's not
gonna take me very long to implement
that thing I was looking a couple of
pages of code or a couple lines of code
so in case you quickly say what kind of
let's move on to the next method and
specify that and you actually you
building this interlocking piece these
interlocking pieces which build up the
story and although you're doing it much
more like a storyteller and yeah you're
writing this prose text it actually has
many of the same characteristics that
you have of programming and uses many of
the same skills if that you have to have
in order to be able to program so it
actually it works amazingly well and it
also feels like programming in a strange
sort of way even though you know haven't
written in any line of code other than
you know throws new illegal argument
exception throws new not implement
runtime error no committed yet right
that's the only piece of code that
actually is in there and likewise the
when you actually have done that a
specification like that you don't have a
very good idea of I mean you understand
the API understand the story you're now
in a really good position to actually
write clients example clients like how
would a client do this well I know I've
provided mechanisms like that so you can
actually write those clients you can
certainly write the tests Suites which
are generally you know coming from the
client side as well so you can write
those and then a lot of cases it's it
feels more like filling in the
implementation its way of describe it
it's not a major challenge because in
fact in working out the details of the
specification making the decisions there
at that level you've actually decided
there are not chef what how the thing is
going to actually hang together in some
sense you're kind of advocating
driven development and or or seeing it
the other way around many people say
that test-driven development helps you
build good api's and you just kind of
explain why yes the only issue I have
with the purest test-driven development
is that if you're in the test-driven
development you're writing the code and
you're writing the tests that test that
code but what you're actually not
writing in the things is the story wait
yes you know don't actually write down
that that specification and so you're
where you end up is in a good place in
one regard in that you actually you've
got the program it does what you wanted
to do and you've got actually a test so
test Suites that actually verify that
the program does what it wants to do and
both of those are really really great
assets what you don't have is an actual
story that you can tell the client but
you could do that afterwards I mean you
have a level head yes you could do that
afterwards but I would actually suggest
that you'll get even better results if
you do it first I don't disagree then
you actually go in and and and say look
the first and foremost the most
important thing is what this API is
going to feel like to its consumers and
make that your primary focus right the
API specs yeah then tests and
implementation will follow naturally
from that and in the end if you follow
that way of doing it not only do you end
up with the program that does what you
want the test Suites the test what you
want but you've got the spec which is
what the clients yeah consumers need in
order to be able to use the API so you
get all three of them out of the same
same process earlier I had mentioned
that that I wanted to start this
dialogue with developers about how they
understood api's and essentially what
what they thought was going on in in
something that all of us believe to be
obvious and I'm trying to sort of
challenge people to think that there may
be
something there may be actual personal
differences going on amongst us that
we're not talking about but actually
have a big bearing so the question I
think is is what you're saying basically
is that different people have different
kind of personalities characteristics
and they they look different at the
problem of API design yes I I've noticed
I've noticed quite you know market
difference in such all the people that
I've worked with over the years and what
did IBM and in in formalized there's it
I've always seen a wide variety of
practices and sort of views of the
things although it's it's very very
subtle so one of the things that feels
very important to me is that as
programmers we actually have this this
interest and we we get paid as as
professional programmers to build
systems that do things right it's that's
the heart of programming that it's it's
a very active process you know that
engages us mentally and the thing that
we're building is something which
actually physically does something else
or the information processing wise and
so it's we have this bias I think very
strong bias for action I do have things
in that side of program if that's what
has attracted many of us to the
programming profession that's what's
selected it's why our employers have
they're selected this or college
programs is because we got somehow
became fascinated at a relatively early
age in most cases most of us with this
mechanism and being able to control it
and make it do what we wanted it to do
and that is a very very important
property that we have and we share as
programmers but I think we share them to
different degrees
and part of the the way I look at it is
there are certain kinds of tasks
programming tasks which we can all
relate to that sort of illicit is
somewhat of a you know a fairly visceral
gut level reaction as to how we would
approach it so I if I told you you know
there's this database that's over here
it's got certain data in it you're gonna
have to use this you know wonky API that
you know here in order to be able to get
at it I know you're not familiar with it
but you're gonna have to actually use
that I'm sorry and I need certain data
taken out analyzed I need a report and I
need it tomorrow yeah I know I put you
in this particular situation and asked
how you would go about doing it
and the kinds of things that you
probably wouldn't even give a seconds
font in the way I had framed the problem
if you wouldn't think about carefully
reading API documentation error handling
rare conditions or writing test Suites
or any of that you'd probably just jump
- I'm gonna wing it I'm going to go in
there yeah I can be in the machine with
the machine I can start building this
thing I can actually start googling for
[Music]
snippets that use the API is still in or
take other people's programs examples
and things like that and you know mutate
them till they work debug them and
things like that and really just live
living in the moment
with the actual program and that
particular aspect is I think something
which we all share yeah to some extent
people make this as essentially a
recreational programming I know people
who go home at night and know exactly
that kind of thing for that kind of sort
of thrill that but it's also striking
that when you look at how that kind of
programming how it relates to what we do
day to day as professional programmers
you know writing an industrial
it's sort of commercial software there's
actually it's related but it's really
quite quite different and the the kinds
of things that are really important to
us on a day to day basis
are are familiar with us but we have to
deal with the fact that we're writing a
program here but it's going to run
somewhere else on somebody else's
machine and it has to make sense in
their world so there's this just this
disconnection between where we're
writing and testing it and where it's
already got to work so we have to pay
attention to a lot more stuff than we
did in this other kind of thing the
program is getting much bigger then you
know something that can be written in a
day and that's it really important
oh the program's gonna live much longer
it's actually gonna take a team of
people working together to actually
build this thing it's not just the sort
of one lone wolf program they're at
night and all of these kinds of things
are different some different contexts
for the programming the particular thing
that's striking is that that kind of
guerrilla program is skill when you
actually go right in there
really goes for this mechanistic side of
computation right a part of computation
has to do do things but the whole side
of computing systems having to do with
api's and the scrutiny of how we break
down a large system into pieces that we
can get our heads around that side of
things isn't addressed by that
mechanistic side of things cause more
conceptual thinking yeah and what we're
doing as programmers is we're actually
playing this double game where a were
definitely going for the mechanistic
thing we have to build something that
does things but we also have to keep all
these other factors in mind including we
have to have to build a system that we
can actually understand the most of us
multiple people on the team can actually
share it can be evolved over a long
period of time all of that kind of stuff
has to be has to be done and the things
that have to do with the scrutiny is a
program and how we understand it are
essentially not the
mechanistic property that and so one
common failure mode
I would I've seen many times I would
describe as a programmer has gone over
to the dark side because they've they've
I believe got caught up with the
mechanistic side of programming and it
has been such a powerful force
psychically in terms of their things
that they've actually forgotten some of
the other things because they were just
sucked into make this work and I think
that that's a really important thing to
realize about ourselves that we have
this draw to the mechanism but usually
there's more than the mechanism that's
that's that's important to us and we
have to make sure that we train the
programmers to understand how to sort of
modulate that world and to do the right
things at the right time maybe also a
call for changing some of the
curriculums in in schools to maybe take
that into account a little bit more
explicitly perhaps members know about
this stuff and newbies often don't yes
and I think very much the the kind of I
think of the hackers working on viruses
as not worrying too too much about the
anything other than the mechanistic side
of things they really are in there for
though let's make this system do
something but yes so but I think even
with the training and everything it's
it's important to realize that not all
programmer right have the same degree of
urges like oh and so give everybody that
task they're good at that is actually
one one very smart thing to do if you
have someone who who seems to be drawn
very much to the mechanism they're
probably not going to be very good at
defining api's because that's going to
be antithetical and that is something I
noticed quite a lot in in the modeling
environment where I carefully look at
the people who will do the meta stuff
right metamodels transformations between
between models because thinking meta is
is different from people who who have
more this mechanistic view I think
that's a kind of similar problem
I'm believe it's
that's the same thing going on there
after there's certain kinds of of things
that were we're really good at and am
drawn to but there's also a bunch of
other skills that we need in order to be
able to build these complicated symptoms
okay
we have to wrap this thing up for timely
reasons there anything else you want to
briefly say to leave our listeners with
I actually leave them just with a
challenge to to actually look at their
particular practices either personal
programming practices or practices in
their their organization starting with
their small team and see whether they're
things about their work habits the
methodologies that they're using that
are essentially either pandering to the
mechanistic side and particular
pandering to the mechanistic side to the
detriment they have the non honestok
side rather they ignoring the API is
ignoring the extra testing and things
like that and just going for the thing I
think our built-in natural biases in the
field
give us a were it's almost like there's
a certain force of gravity onto it any
kind of thing which which causes people
to to actually look at at what they're
doing and reflecting that it's really
getting us where we need to go with
fastest yeah I think that's that's a
good thing to do not very nice closing
comment so thank you very much Jim for
being on the show thank you Mary Simon
I've enjoyed this interview very much
good great thanks bye public thanks for
listening to software engineering radio
software engineering radio is an
educational program brought to you by
hillside Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
se - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SA radio team
via the website or you can advertise for
se radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious links and the
slash dot button to contact the team
please send email to team @ s e - radio
net or if it is specific to an episode
please use the comments for
sylheti on the website so other people
can react to your comments this episode
of se radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under the Creative
Commons 2.5 license please see the
website for details thanks to Charlie
Crowell and the pot safe music Network
for the music used in this show the song
is called Vegas hard rock shuffle